Finding Aid for Democratic Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records, 1959-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Democratic Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records 1959-2002 1979-1985
Democratic Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
87303 Bt 2
Files relating to local campaigns and to party organization.
2.3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were transferred by David DeVarti, Chairperson, Ann Arbor Democratic Party, June 1987 and April 1989. Donor No. 7445.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Ann Arbor Democratic Party is the local link between the politicians and people of Ann Arbor and the county and state Democratic Party apparatus. The local party reflects, to varying degrees at different times, the state party's idea that political activities should be decentralized and focused on grassroots issues. The Ann Arbor Democratic Party's purpose is to win elected positions for its candidates in local campaigns. This imperative motivates the secondary functions of building a network of campaign volunteers, raising funds, and getting out the vote. The local party turns only scant attention to its tertiary duty of campaigning for national candidates.
The Ann Arbor Democratic Party papers have been organized in four series: 1959-1970 Materials; 1970-1976 Materials; Campaigns, 1977-1987; and Standing Committees/ Day-to-Day Functioning, 1975-1988. The bulk of the material falls within the compass of the last two series, since the local party generated more files once its members had access to computers. The last two series should be viewed as complementary units; the original files were in such disorder that extensive re-filing of documents was necessary during processing.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Democratic Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Hunter, Larry.; Pierce, Edward, 1930-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- 1959-1970 Materials
  The Pre-1970 series is arranged by type of document or office that created the document.
  - Chairperson (Ted Wilson and Walt Scheider) 1964-1969 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1965-1969 (Box 1)
    (includes letter of Wilson to President Johnson)
  - Handbooks and By-Laws 1965-1970 (Box 1)
  - Issues, General 1962-1966
    - City Issues 1962-1966 (Box 1)
    - Housing 1962-1965 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters and Literature 1964-1970 (Box 1)
  - Platforms 1959-1969 (Box 1)
  - Voting Statistics 1964-1966 (Box 1)
- 1970-1976 Materials, 1975-1976
  The 1970-1976 Materials series focuses on the local 1975-1976 elections and local issues during the whole period. If these extant records are any indication, the Ann Arbor Democratic Party failed to conform to the ideal of a strong grassroots organization. Neil Staebler, the state Democratic Chairman (whose papers are also housed at the Michigan Historical Collections), developed a model of organic party building at the precinct level. The Staebler and George A. Sallade papers offer different and informative insight into the local party of these years.
  - General 1970-1973 (Box 1)
  - General 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Campaigns 1972-1975 (Box 1)
    (including 1974 Charter Revision)
  - Correspondence 1976 (Box 1)
  - Elections 1975
    - April 1975 (Box 1)
    - November 1975 (Box 1)
  - Elections 1976
    - April 1976 (Box 1)
    - November 1976
      - General Materials (Box 1)
      - Campaign Literature (Box 1)
  - Elections Statistics (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee/Board Meeting Minutes 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - General Meeting Minutes 1976 (Box 1)
  - Issues, General 1974-1976
    - City Charter Revision 1974-1976 (Box 1)
    - Community Development Revenue Sharing and Building Grant 1974 (Box 1)
    - DNA Research 1976 (Box 1)
  - Platforms 1970-1974 (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw County Democratic Party 1974-1976 (Box 1)
- Campaigns 1977-1987
  The Campaigns, 1977-1987 series has been arranged chronologically by type of campaign. The primary focus is on the local elections and candidates. Issues pertaining to a certain campaign have been included within that year; this includes ballot proposals as well as issues which candidates created. The material on Ward Campaigns varies year to year and by ward. In general, Wards 1, 3, and 5 are better documented than Wards 2 and 4.
  - Election 1977
    - General Materials 1977 (Box 1)
    - April 1977 Campaign Literature (Box 1)
    - Punch Card Voting 1977 (Box 1)
  - Election 1978
    - General Materials 1978 (Box 1)
    - April 1978 Campaign Literature (Box 1)
    - November 1978 (Box 1)
    - Election Coordination 1978 (Box 1)
    - Mayoral Campaign (Al Wheeler) 1978 (Box 1)
    - Pursell and Carr Voting Records 1978 (Box 1)
    - Statistics 1978 (Box 1)
    - Wards 1978 (Box 1)
  - Election 1979
    - April 1979
      - General Materials 1979 (Box 1)
      - Campaign Literature 1979 (Box 1)
      - Mayoral Campaign (Jamie Kenworthy) 1979 (Box 1)
    - Punch Card Voting 1979 (Box 1)
    - Pursell and Carr Voting Records 1979 (Box 1)
    - Statistics, Campaign Efficiency Index 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - Wards 1979 (Box 1)
  - Election 1980
    - General Materials 1980 (Box 1)
  - Election 1981
    - General Materials, Petitions 1981 (Box 2)
    - Perry Bullard Materials 1981-1983 (Box 2)
    - City Re-apportionment 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - Wards 1981 (Box 2)
  - Election 1982
    - General Material, Campaign Coordination, Nomination 1982 (Box 2)
    - Campaign Literature 1982-1986 (Box 2)
    - State and Congressional 1982 (Box 2)
    - Wards 1982 (Box 2)
    - Ward Directories and Precinct Profiles 1982 (Box 2)
  - Election 1983
    - General, Nominating Committee 1983 (Box 2)
    - Mayoral Campaign (Tom Blessing and Leslie Morris) 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - Wards 1983 (Box 2)
  - Election 1984
    - General Materials 1984 (Box 2)
    - November 1984
      - General Materials 1984 (Box 2)
    - Mayoral Campaign (Bunyan Bryant) 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - Sheriff Primary 1984 (Box 2)
    - Wards 1984 (Box 2)
  - Election 1985
    - General Materials, Issues 1985 (Box 2)
    - Mayoral Campaign (Ed Pierce) 1985 (Box 2)
  - Election 1987
    - Council Campaigns Materials 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - General Material 1985 (Box 2)
  - Chairperson (Tom Murray) 1982-1984 (Box 2)
  - Chairperson 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - City Party Organization 1981-1985 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1977-1985
    - General 1977-1986 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - Victor Adamo 1979-1979 (Box 2)
    - David Cahill 1977-1985 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Events and Projects 1975-1985
    - Winter Warming and Other Parties 1975-1985 (Box 2)
    - Art Fair Concession Stand 1977-1981 (Box 2)
    - Voter Vans 1985 (Box 2)
  - Handbooks and By-Laws 1979-1986 (Box 2)
  - Issues 1982-1986
    - General 1982-1986 (Box 2)
    - Voter Registration 1984 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter
    - September 1974-June 1977, August 1982-September 1988 (Box 2)
    - September 1977-May 1981 (newsprint copies) (Box 2)
  - Platforms 1978-1985 (Box 3)
- Standing Committees/Day-To-Day Functioning 1975-1988
  The Standing Committees/Day-to-Day Functioning, 1975-1988 series provides insight into a well-documented, better-organized local party. The Standing Committee files are especially illuminating in that they paradigmatically reflect Staebler's model of local party organizations. The Victor Adamo correspondence documents both incoming and outgoing letters of the party chairperson between 1977 and 1979. The David Cahill correspondence should be examined in that he served the party in several capacities: First Ward Chairperson, Vice-Chair for Organization, and Data Service Liaison. In these capacities, Cahill serves as a unique prism through which to view the Ann Arbor Democratic Party activities. Other materials in this series focus on broad issues that were not necessarily contained in any one year's campaign platform, the by laws and yearly platforms from 1978 to 1985, and the events and projects of the party -- both politically oriented ones and social outings.
  - General Material 1985 (Box 2)
  - Chairperson (Tom Murray) 1982-1984 (Box 2)
  - Chairperson 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - City Party Organization 1981-1985 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1977-1985
    - General 1977-1986 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - Victor Adamo 1979-1979 (Box 2)
    - David Cahill 1977-1985 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Events and Projects 1975-1985
    - Winter Warming and Other Parties 1975-1985 (Box 2)
    - Art Fair Concession Stand 1977-1981 (Box 2)
    - Voter Vans 1985 (Box 2)
  - Handbooks and By-Laws 1979-1986 (Box 2)
  - Issues 1982-1986
    - General 1982-1986 (Box 2)
    - Voter Registration 1984 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter
    - September 1974-June 1977, August 1982-September 1988 (Box 2)
    - September 1977-May 1981 (newsprint copies) (Box 2)
  - Platforms 1978-1985 (Box 3)
  - Standing Committees 1977-1988
    - Community Relations Task Force 1982 (Box 3)
    - Data Services (Jim Dreis) 1981-1985
      - Reports 1982-1986 (Box 3)
    - Executive Board 1977-1983
      - Board Meeting Minutes 1977-1988 (Box 3)
    - Finances 1979-1985 (Box 3)
    - Voter Development 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - Wards 1984-1986 (Box 3)
  - Washtenaw County Democratic Party 1982-1985 (Box 3)
- Later materials
  - Photographs: portraits of Democratic mayoral and council candidates (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous records 1982-1987 (Box 3)
  - Annual dinner programs 1998-2002 (Box 3)